{"tossups": [{"question": "An Epicurean-esque philosophical school from this country believed in skepticism and empiricist materialism and was heavily criticized at a conference of all faiths held in what is now this country in 1578. Arthur Schopenhauer was influenced by the philosophy of this country when he wrote<em> The World</em> <em>as Will and Representation</em>. A philosophical lineage from this country includes the great thinker Shankara and is divided into dualist and non-dualist branches called \u201cdvaita\u201d [d\u2019vi-ta] and \u201cadvaita\u201d [ahd-vi-ta] respectively. For the point, name this country, home to Vedanta and other philosophical schools like Yoga.", "answer": "<b> India</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "One casualty of this battle was a man who had earlier been appointed head of the Hawaiian Navy, but gave up the job when he found that Kamehameha III had no ships; that man, Augustus van Horne Ellis, died in this battle while leading an attack through the Triangular Field. On the first day of this battle, forces under Henry Heth overran First Corps [\u201ccore\u201d] troops stationed at McPherson Ridge. The Peach Orchard and Devil\u2019s Den were key locations at this battle, where Joshua Chamberlain\u2019s volunteer regiment led a successful defense of Little Round Top. For the point, name this 1863 battle, the turning point of the Civil War in Pennsylvania.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Gettysburg</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Russell Hadley reconstructed this man\u2019s face before he left Los Angeles for Atlanta. Loyd Jowers was sued for an action committed by this man, who used the alias Eric Starvo Galt. This man was hit with an extra year in prison after escaping from Brushy Mountain State Prison. Jack Kershaw promoted the idea that a conspirator named \u201cRaul\u201d framed this man, who was caught with a Canadian passport in England. A 1968 murder at the Lorraine Motel was committed by, for the point, what assassin of Martin Luther King?", "answer": "James Earl<b> Ray</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "John Bradmore used honey as an antiseptic when he operated on an arrow wound in this man\u2019s face. Holy Roman Emperor Sigismund and this ruler signed the Treaty of Canterbury, acknowledging land claims in France. Thomas Beaufort served this king, who executed his former friend, Sir John Oldcastle. A plot to replace this king with Edmund Mortimer ended with a trial at Southampton. After capturing Harfleur, this man won a critical battle in a muddy field that would lead to the Treaty of Troyes with Charles VI. For the point, name this English king who won the Battle of Agincourt.", "answer": "<b> Henry V</b> of England (accept<b> Henry of Monmouth</b>; prompt on Henry)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Politicians from this man\u2019s country opposed him in the Caravelle Manifesto. The efforts of ambassador Henry Cabot Lodge Jr. and Cable 243 led to this man\u2019s death. This man alienated Buddhists in the Xa Loi Pagoda raids following a self-immolation by a monk, and he instituted the Strategic Hamlet Program to shelter peasants. This anti-Communist Vietnamese leader opposed Ho Chi Minh\u2019s Viet Cong guerillas. For the point, name this first President of South Vietnam who was assassinated in 1963.", "answer": "<b> Ngo</b> Dinh Diem", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Corpses were often thrown into this body of water after state executions carried out at the Gemonian Stairs. The Via Flaminia\u2019s crossing of this body of water was the site of a battle whose victor was inspired to paint the Chi-Rho on the shields of his forces. Maxentius\u2019 head was thrown into this river after he lost the Battle of Milvian Bridge, resulting in the ascension of Constantine as emperor. For the point, name this river that flows through Rome.", "answer": "<b> Tiber</b> River", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This scientist\u2019s repeated attempts to enlist in the Navy during World War II were denied on grounds of age, being underweight, and being a math professor at Vassar, a job valuable to the war effort. While working on the Mark I at Harvard, this scientist theorized that, despite the \u201cfact\u201d that computers could only perform arithmetic, an English-based language could be implemented via a compiler that she developed. COBOL was inspired by the work of, for the point, what American rear admiral and computer scientist?", "answer": "Grace<b> Hopper</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "At this battle, a soldier who had been earlier dismissed because of an eye infection charged enemy lines alone to redeem his name. That man, Aristodemus, died at this battle, where Arimnestus threw a large rock to kill the enemy commander, Mardonius. This battle, which was fought at the same time as a naval engagement at Mycale [mi-kah-lee], was won by Pausanias\u2019 troops near Boeotia [boh-ee-she-uh]. For the point, name this 479 BC battle, the final land battle of Xerxes\u2019 invasion of Greece.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Plataea</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This company\u2019s productions of<em> Parade</em> and<em> Pulcinella</em> featured design by Pablo Picasso. The Great Depression spelled the end of this company, which premiered<em> L\u2019Apr`es-midi d\u2019un faune</em> [lap-reh mi-dee doon fawn], marking Vaslav Nijinsky\u2019s first work as a choreographer. The riotous premiere of<em> The Rite of</em> <em>Spring</em> was produced by this company. Sergei Diaghilev founded, for the point, what ballet company that, despite its name, was based in Paris, not Moscow?", "answer": "<b> Ballets Russes</b> ([\u201cballet\u201d roose], but be lenient)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Dance"}, {"question": "This event\u2019s victims were later brought to the Koptyaki forest and thrown down the Ganina Yama mineshaft. The approach of the Czechoslovak Legion prompted the perpetrators to carry out this event in Yekaterinburg. Diamonds sewn into nightclothes may have temporarily protected the victims of this event, including Maria, Tatiana, and Anastasia. For the point, name this July 1918 massacre of the Imperial family of Russia.", "answer": "<b> execution</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> massacre</b>, etc.) of the<b> Romanov</b>s (accept<b> execution</b> of Tsar <b>Nicholas II</b> and his family, including Tsarina Alexandra, Olga, Alexei, Maria, Tatiana, and Anastasia) (15) In this state, over $200,000 worth of money was stolen from a series of banks in an 1864 attack planned by Bennett Young. That action, the St. Albans Raid, was the northernmost battle of the Civil War. John Burgoyne\u2019s men lost to a coalition led by John Stark and Seth Warner ten miles from this state\u2019s city of Bennington. This state was a republic from 1777 to 1791, when it joined the union as the first non-colonial state. For the point, name this 14th US state, which is home to Burlington. ANSWER:<b> Vermont</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Before attacking this empire, an army first attacked the island of Pun\u00b4a, before landing at Tumbes. This empire\u2019s southern expansion was ended at the Maule River by the Mapuche people, and the Battle of Cajamarca secured its decline. A ruler of this empire named Hu\u00b4ascar died fighting his brother Atahualpa, who was then ransomed for a room of gold by Spanish conquistadors. For the point, name this Quechua-speaking empire that built Machu Picchu and was centered at Cuzco, Peru until it was conquered by Francisco Pizarro.", "answer": "<b> Inca</b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The Independent Party of Color was dissolved in this country following the 1912 Little Race War. Thom\u00b4as Estrada Palma served as the first president of this country. A 1903 treaty between the U.S. and this country, along with the Platt Amendment, helped secure an American naval base at this country\u2019s Guantanamo Bay. For the point, name this Caribbean island country that was led by Fidel Castro.", "answer": "<b> Cuba</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "After committing a double murder in this state, Erik and Lyle Menendez went on a spending spree and appear, sitting courtside, in the background of Mark Jackson\u2019s 1990 basketball trading card. In this state in 2003, Oregon-based songwriter Elliot Smith died of stab wounds; the autopsy was unable to determine who wielded the knife. The Symbionese Liberation Army kidnapped Patty Hearst in this state in 1974. Elizabeth Short, known as the Black Dahlia, was mysteriously murdered in 1947 in, for the point, what state where the Manson family operated and killed Sharon Tate in Los Angeles?", "answer": "<b> California</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s government arrested the spy Wolfgang Lotz, then set him free in a prisoner exchange in 1968. This leader, who organized a brief United Republic with Syria that lasted for three years, worked with Mohammed Naguib of the Free Officers Movement to overthrow King Farouk. The ambitious Aswan High Dam project was completed by this man, who banned the Muslim Brotherhood and faced a combined French and British invasion after nationalizing the Suez Canal. For the point, identify this leader of Egypt in the 1960s.", "answer": "Gamal Abdel<b> Nasser</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In the city of Brauron, a festival to this deity had young girls wear saffron robes and pretend to be bears. It became illegal to mention the name Herostratus after he burned down a temple to this deity in the 4th century BC. Actaeon was turned into a deer after he saw this goddess naked. This child of Leto served as midwife for the birth of her twin sibling. For the point, name this deity whose temple at Ephesus was one of the seven wonders of the ancient world, the Greek goddess of the hunt.", "answer": "<b> Artemis</b> (accept<b> Diana</b> before \u201cGreek\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This location was captured after troops scaled the Sugar Loaf peak, allowing them to train cannons on this location and the nearby Mount Independence. John Burgoyne retook this location after Ethan Allen and the Green Mountain Boys first put it in Continental control two years prior. A \u201cnoble train of artillery\u201d under Henry Knox helped transport guns from this location to Boston. For the point, name this vital fort located at the southern end of Lake Champlain in New York.", "answer": "Fort<b> Ticonderoga</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man took power shortly after a battle at Shimultai, which garnered him the support of Alghu in the Toluid civil war against Ariq Boke. After his forces gained control following the battle of Yamen, this man established a new capital at Dadu, which was visited by the Venetian merchant Marco Polo. The divine wind kamikaze famously thwarted this man\u2019s attempts to invade Japan. For the point, name this founder of the Yuan Dynasty and grandson of Genghis Khan.", "answer": "<b> Kublai</b> Khan", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "An invented man named Isidorus Pacensis was mistakenly given credit for writing about this battle in the Mozarabic Chronicle. This battle was prompted after a disaster at the Garonne River forced Odo, the duke of Aquitaine, to call for aid. The losing side in this battle repeatedly charged uphill with cavalry and withdrew after the death of Abd al-Rahman. Fought at St. Martin\u2019s Abbey, this battle led its victor to be known as \u201cthe Hammer.\u201d For the point, name this 732 battle where Charles Martel thwarted the Muslim expansion into Europe.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Tours</b> (accept Battle of<b> Poitiers</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, Thomas Macdonough won a battle on Lake Champlain called the \u201cFalse Nile.\u201d In this war, Henry Proctor lost a battle near Moraviantown to William Henry Harrison, which preceeded a battle in which a commander declared, \u201cWe have met the enemy and they are ours.\u201d Oliver Hazard Perry won the Battle of Lake Erie during, for the point, what war that included the burning of Washington D.C. and was ended by the Treaty of Ghent in 1815?", "answer": "War of<b> 1812</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Michael of the Peaked Beard was an early defector to this empire. According to legend, this empire\u2019s founder had a dream in which he planted a tree that grew to cover wide swaths of the world. This empire\u2019s early rivals included the Karamanid and Ak Koyunlu, and this empire\u2019s custom of strangling unsuccessful brothers of its rulers was encoded into law by a ruler who defeated Constantine XI, Mehmed the Conqueror. For the point, name this empire that made Constantinople its capital after capturing it from the Byzantines.", "answer": "<b> Ottoman</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}